{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A 1911 revolt in this city's Wuchang district led to the Xinhai [[SHIN-\"HIGH\"]] Revolution, which ended the Qing [[CHING]] Dynasty. One preliminary attack on this city was repelled in the \"Two-Eighteen Air Battle.\" The Nationalist government moved its primary operations to this city after the fall of Nanjing. After a four-month long battle, this city fell to the Japanese in 1938. For ten points, name this historical transportation hub and \"Chicago of China\" where the coronavirus that caused the COVID-19 pandemic was first discovered.",
      "answer": "Wuhan"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man attempted to have his cadets punished after they drew caricatures of him with the nickname \"square box\" due to his exceptionally large shoe size. The preserved hide of this man's horse, Little Sorrel, is on display at the Virginia Military Institute, where this man once taught. This general died from pneumonia brought upon by his amputation after he was shot by friendly fire at the Battle of Chancellorsville. For ten points, name this Confederate general who earned his famous nickname due to his heroics at Bull Run.",
      "answer": "Thomas \"Stonewall\" Jackson or Thomas Jonathan Jackson"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2020, DNA paternity tests revealed that one holder of this position had fathered a child out of wedlock with Sybille de Selys Longchamps. The first holder of this position declined to take up the throne of Greece under the 1830 London Protocol. One man who took this title in 2013 resides at the Palace of Laeken [[LAY-kehn]] and claimed this title after the sudden abdication of his father, Albert II. For ten points, name this title, once held by a man who was known for atrocities committed in the Congo Free State, Leopold II.",
      "answer": [
        "King of Belgium or King of the Belgians",
        "or Koning der Belgen",
        "or Roi des Belges",
        "or König der Belgier",
        "synonyms such as \"monarch\"",
        "\"ruler\" in place of \"king\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Due most likely to the docking of the SS Talune, over 90 percent of this region's residents became infected with the Spanish Flu. A proposed colonial flag for this region featured three white palm trees on a red shield. This region's second civil war ended with the Tripartite Convention of 1899, which divided administration of this region between Germany and the United States. For ten points, name this region that contained the last colonial acquisition of the German Empire and the only U.S. territory south of the equator.",
      "answer": [
        "Samoa or Independent State of Samoa",
        "or Malo Saʻoloto Tutoʻatasi o Sāmoa",
        "American Samoa",
        "German Samoa",
        "Deutsch Samoa 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A building named for this man had to sand down panels on the Founders Room to avoid concentrating sunlight on nearby residences. Acoustic designers Minoru Nagata and Yasuhisa Toyota created the interior of that building named for this man, whose exterior architecture was designed by Frank Gehry and which is the home of the Los Angeles Philharmonic. Another complex named after this man contains long-running sections such as Critter Country, Adventureland, and Main Street U.S.A. For ten points, identify this animator and namesake of \"Land\" and \"World\" theme park complexes in California and Florida.",
      "answer": [
        "Walt Disney or Walter Elias Disney",
        "Disneyland and Walt Disney World",
        "Walt Disney Concert Hall"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This territory is home to a namesake petrel, also known as the Cahow [[KAY-how]], which was thought to have been extinct for three hundred years until its rediscovery in 1951. While en route to Jamestown, George Somers’s shipwrecked fleet used smaller boats to colonize this island. During the English Civil War, this island's governor, William Sayle, moved its anti-royalist inhabitants to the Bahamas. For ten points, identify this overseas British dependency that names a “Triangle” known for odd disappearances.",
      "answer": [
        "Bermuda",
        "Bermuda Triangle"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The length of the case Swidler & Berlin v. United States, a case involving this man's administration, led to the demise of the independent counsel at the federal level. Kenneth Starr exonerated this man, but not his wife, in the so-called \"Travelgate,\" which dealt with the sudden firing of seven employees in an act of cronyism. Linda Tripp leaked intimate phone calls between a White House intern and this man, leading to perjury charges and an impeachment trial. The Whitewater and Lewinsky scandals rocked the administration of, for ten points, what Democratic president?",
      "answer": [
        "Bill Clinton or William Jefferson Clinton",
        "William Jefferson Blythe III"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One psychologist used his experiences in one of these places to outline his theory of logotherapy. One philosopher controversially claimed that keeping a positive outlook was necessary for survival in these places in the book Man's Search for Meaning. One of the primary developers of these places was used as an example of the \"banality of evil\" in Hannah Arendt's book Eichmann in Jerusalem. Victor Frankl wrote about his time in, for ten points, what locations where the majority of killings during the Holocaust took place?",
      "answer": [
        "Nazi concentration camps",
        "Konzentrationslager",
        "Extermination camps",
        "Death camps",
        "Killing centers",
        "specific examples like Auschwitz"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One god who appeared as one of these animals, Orochi, was defeated by the hero Susano'o [[soo-SAH-nah OH]], who found the \"Grass-Cutting Sword\" in its tail. A traditional symbol of medicine, the Rod of Asclepius, depicts these creatures, which were allowed to freely crawl near patients in Ancient Greece. One legend claims conquistador Hernan Cortes was mistake for Quetzalcoatl, a \"feathered\" example of, for ten points, what type of reptile, which supposedly tempted Adam and Eve in the Garden of Eden?",
      "answer": [
        "Snakes",
        "Serpents",
        "Dragons before \"Asclepius\" is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This individual’s tweet about receiving the COVID-19 vaccine was branded by Ted Cruz as “government propaganda.” Nearly 50 years earlier, this character was seen receiving an injection in a public service campaign to get more children vaccinated against measles. NASA invited this character to join the Challenger flight to teach kids about space, and Mitt Romney said that he loves this character, despite wanting to cut taxpayer money from PBS. From 1969 to 2018, Caroll Spinney portrayed, for ten points, what Sesame Street character, an eight foot-tall avian?",
      "answer": "Big Bird 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This agreement was first put forward by James Wilson to bridge support for the House of Representatives. Alexander Hamilton asked, \"Would it be just to impose a singular burden, without conferring some adequate advantage?\" in debating this agreement. This compromise proposed \"adding to the whole Number of free Persons, including those bound to Service for a Term of Years, and excluding Indians not taxed.\" For ten points, name this 1787 compromise over the method by which enslaved persons would be counted in determining a state's population.",
        "answer": "Three-Fifths Compromise"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This abolitionist pointed to the Constitution as an anti-slavery document in a debate with George Thompson about the Three-Fifths Compromise. He later founded the newspaper The North Star.",
        "answer": [
          "Frederick Douglass",
          "Frederick Augustus Washington Bailey"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Along this structure, a dispute over the repatriation of Magyar POWs led in part to the Revolt of the Czechoslovak Legion. Alexander Kolchak's government was weakened when parts of this structure between Chita and Krasnoyarsk [[krass-nuh-YARSK]] were destroyed by partisans. Until the completion of the Circum-Baikal Railway, a train ferry was used to connect two parts of this route. Major cities on this route include Yekaterinburg [[yeh-KAT-eh-rin-burg]] and Novosibirsk [[noh-voh-see-BEERSK]]. For ten points, name this longest railway in the world, stretching from Moscow to Vladivodstok.",
        "answer": [
          "Trans–Siberian Railway or Transsibirskaya magistral",
          "or TSR",
          "\"Railroad\" in place of \"Railway\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The construction of the Trans-Siberian Railway was largely orchestrated by which prime minister of Nicholas II? Considered the Russian Empire's first prime minister, this man produced the October Manifesto to quell the 1905 Russian Revolution.",
        "answer": [
          "Sergei Witte ] or Count Sergei Yulyevich Witte",
          "or Sergius Witte"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Process Certification Scheme named for this city aimed to prevent a certain good from being sold to finance paramilitaries. Esau Damon was the first person to discover that good, a precious mineral, in Colesberg Kopje, located in this city. The Honoured Dead Memorial in this city commemorates soldiers who died during a Boer War-era siege of this city over its valuable mines. For ten points, name this South African city known worldwide for its diamonds.",
        "answer": "Kimberley"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What diamond company, financed by Alfred Beit and originally owned by Cecil Rhodes, profited from several Kimberley mines.",
        "answer": "De Beers Group 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman and six of her children were killed by members of the Siwanoy tribe during Kieft’s War. Governor Henry Vane often attended meetings hosted by this woman, who eventually settled on Aquidneck [[ah-KWID-nehk]] Island. Mary Dyer was the only person to stand up for this woman when she was tried in Boston in connection with the Antinomian Controversy. For ten points, name this early American religious reformer who was expelled from the Massachusetts Bay Colony for her heretical views.",
        "answer": "Anne Hutchinson or Anne Marbury"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hutchinson was encouraged to establish a settlement at Portsmouth by which man who founded a colony at Providence Plantations?",
        "answer": "Roger Williams"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A movement to expand legal rights for these people was opposed by the \"Brunswick clubs\" and was largely financed by \"forty-shillingers\" in an association founded by Richard Shiel and Daniel O'Connell. An 1829 Relief Act benefiting these people was championed by the Duke of Wellington. The \"emancipation\" of these people removed the requirement to renounce transubstantiation before taking civil office. For ten points, name this group that was discriminated against in England with the slogan \"No Popery.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Roman Catholics",
          "Papist"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The only major legal disability for British Catholics that was not repealed in the 1820s were the exclusionary provisions of this 1701 act dictating the line of succession to the crown.",
        "answer": "Act of Settlement Editor's Note: A 2013 amendment to the Act of Settlement added persons married to a Catholic to the line of succession, but the monarch must belong to the Church of England."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This region was the site of the 1872 salvage hearings of the American merchant brigantine, Mary Celeste, after it was mysteriously discovered adrift off the Azores. The failed plan of Nazi Germany to capture this region during World War II was referred to as \"Operation Felix.\" According to Article X [[TEN]] in the Peace of Utrecht, Spain ceded Minorca and this region to Great Britain. Located in the Iberian Peninsula, for ten points, what region on the southern tip of Spain has a namesake rock?",
        "answer": [
          "Gibraltar",
          "Rock of Gibraltar"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Because it was a British protectorate, what singer-songwriter married Yoko Ono in Gibraltar in 1969?",
        "answer": "John Lennon or John Winston Ono Lennon 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, William Hodson ordered the execution of three princes at the “Bloody Gate.\" Colin Campbell reinforced a garrison during this event, which allowed for an evacuation of women and children from Lucknow. Bahadur Shah II was exiled to Burma following this event, which was initiated by a controversy over animal fat used in rifle cartridges. For ten points, identify this 1857 \"Mutiny\" that resulted in the British Crown taking control of India from the British East India Company.",
        "answer": [
          "Sepoy Mutiny or Sepoy Rebellion",
          "or Indian Rebellion of 1857"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Khem Singh Bendi, who helped British troops quell an uprising during the Sepoy Mutiny, was fictionalized in the story On The City Wall by this author, who also wrote the Just-So Stories.",
        "answer": "Rudyard Kipling or Joseph Rudyard Kipling"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In an event in this year, a politician told one group, “I am the past, you are the future. I embrace you.” During that event in this year, a ten percent real wage increase was secured in the Grenelle [[greh-NEHL]] Agreements. During this year, the Action Programme secured greater freedom of speech in a country that championed the slogan “socialism with a human face.” A series of student protests in France occurred in this year in which Alexander Dubcek [[DOOB-chek]] oversaw the Prague Spring. For ten points, name this year in which European newspapers published accounts of the death of Martin Luther King, Jr.",
        "answer": "1968"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the invasion of Czechoslovakia in 1968, the country entered into a period defined by this term, during which the pre-Prague Spring status quo was restored.",
        "answer": [
          "Normalization or Normalizace",
          "or Normalizácia"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Valley Forge",
      "prompt": "Concerning Valley Forge, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Continental Army who directed his troops there in the winter of 1777- 78.",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pennsylvania city whose fall to the British led to the Continental army fleeing to Valley Forge.",
          "answer": "Philadelphia"
        },
        {
          "question": "French marquis who assisted in the reorganization of the Continental army during the winter of 1777.",
          "answer": "Marquis de Lafayette"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prussian drillmaster who taught tactics to American forces using his \"Blue Book.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Friedrich Wilhelm von Steuben or Baron von Steuben",
            "or Friedrich Wilhelm August Heinrich Ferdinand von Steuben"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Form of disease resistance which predates vaccination, used at Valley Forge to prevent smallpox outbreaks.",
          "answer": "Inoculation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Victor at the Battle of Guilford Courthouse who oversaw supply management as Quartermaster General.",
          "answer": "Nathanael Greene"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pennsylvania battle fought during the evacuation in a failed attempt to eradicate the Continental Army.",
          "answer": "Battle of White Marsh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Connecticut soldier who wrote a \"narrative\" covering the common soldier's experience.",
          "answer": "Joseph Plumb Martin 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Third Republic",
      "prompt": "Concerning the French Third Republic, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Politician and general who led \"Free France\" after the fall of the Third Republic.",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle or Charles André Joseph Marie de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor whose government collapsed following the Franco-Prussian War, leading to the formation of the Third Republic.",
          "answer": "Napoleon III"
        },
        {
          "question": "1890s trial of a French officer of Jewish origin which led to his false imprisonment.",
          "answer": "Dreyfus Affair or L'affaire Dreyfus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leftist movement which seized Paris in 1871 and was brutally put down by General Patrice de MacMahon.",
          "answer": [
            "Communards",
            "the Paris Commune"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Aggressive nationalism which became the nickname of Georges Ernest Boulanger.",
          "answer": [
            "Revanchism",
            "General Revanche"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of agreements between France and the UK which tied the two closer diplomatically.",
          "answer": [
            "Entente Cordiale",
            "Cordial Agreement"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "French Socialist prime minister immediately before and after World War Two.",
          "answer": "Léon Blum or André Léon Blum"
        },
        {
          "question": "1904 affair in which it was exposed that General Louis André was hampering the careers of Catholic and royalist officers.",
          "answer": [
            "Affair of the Casseroles",
            "Affair of the Cards",
            "or Affaire des Fiches 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Qin [[CHIN]] Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Concerning the short-lived Qin Dynasty, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Founder who declared himself the first Emperor of China.",
          "answer": [
            "Qin Shi Huang or Shihuangdi",
            "King Zheng of Qin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Material used to make an \"Army\" at the Mausoleum of the First Qin Emperor.",
          "answer": "Terracotta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Concept used to legitimize the emperor's right to rule China.",
          "answer": [
            "Mandate of Heaven or Tiānmìng",
            "Heaven's Will"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Strict philosophical school of Shang Yang.",
          "answer": [
            "Legalism or Fajia",
            "Legalist"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Chaotic period of Chinese history ended by the Qin reunification.",
          "answer": "Warring States or Zhànguó Shídài"
        },
        {
          "question": "Han historian who claimed they buried over 400 Confucian scholars alive in his Records of the Grand Historian.",
          "answer": "Sima Qian"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nomadic confederacy of the steppes which Meng Tian partially conquered.",
          "answer": "Xiongnu Confederation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second emperor and brother of the heir who was forced to commit suicide following a coup by Zhao Gao.",
          "answer": "Qin Er Shi or Ying Huhai 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader lost one election due to the Otsego sheriff’s office being vacant. As governor of New York, this man rejected a gerrymandering proposal from Alexander Hamilton. This leader argued for undivided government in Federalist Paper Number (20 pts)",
        "2. On the Supreme Court, this leader established the “cases and controversies” precedent, in contrast to the more activist philosophy of John Marshall. A 1795 (10 pts)",
        "treaty between the U.S. and the UK is named for, for ten points, what first Supreme Court Chief Justice?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John Jay",
        "Jay's Treaty"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man accepted twenty thousand marks as part of an agreement with an English royal known as the Treaty of Le Goulet [[goo-LEH]]. This man decided to take an overland route through the Alps rather than a sea route from Marseille [[mahr- SAY]] before reconvening with another group in (20 pts)",
        "Messina. Isabella of Hainault [[ay-NOH]] was married to this man, who defeated an army led by Otto IV at a battle fought in Flanders in 1214. This victor at Bouvines [[boo-VEEN]] (10 pts)",
        "allied with Richard the Lionheart during the Third Crusade. For ten points, name this French king given the epithet “Augustus.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Philip II of France or Philip Augustus",
        "\"Philippe\" in place of \"Philip\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One U.S. author, whose parents fled this country, wrote The Pearl That Broke Its Shell before running for Maryland's 6th congressional district. An author born in this country wrote a \"mother-daughter story\" in which Mariam kills Rasheed with (20 pts)",
        "a shovel to save the relationship of Laila and Tariq [[tah-REEK]]. A violent Communist coup in this country inspired a novel in which Assef sexually assaults the Hazara boy, Hassan. Khaled Hosseini (10 pts)",
        "set The Kite Runner in, for ten points, what country, ruled by the Taliban?"
      ],
      "answer": "Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The sacred fire in this non-Greek deity’s temple was extinguished by Theodosius I in 394 AD. In a festival celebrating this deity, a donkey was dressed in a garland of flowers as it was believed that the same animal saved the deity from the god Priapus [[pry-AY-pus]]. (20 pts)",
        "Offerings to this deity often included a sacred bread called the \"mola salsa.\" At this deity’s temple, mothers (10 pts)",
        "arrived barefoot and left offerings in exchange for blessings. For ten points, name this Ancient Roman goddess of the hearth who was attended to by namesake \"Virgin\" priestesses."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Vesta",
        "Vestal Virgins 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Up to sixty percent of this syndicate's membership is made up of a former untouchable group known as the Burakumin, or \"hamlet people,\" according to journalist David E. Kaplan. Grave offenses by members in this organization result in Yubitsume [[yoo-bit-SOO-meh]], (20 pts)",
        "or the ritual cutting off of one's own little finger. Citing their own ninkyo honor code, this general class of crime (10 pts)",
        "organizations delivered supplies to those affected by the 2011 Tōhoku catastrophe. The Japanese word for \"gangsters\" is used to refer to, for ten points, what array of crime organizations in Japan?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yakuza",
        "Gokudō",
        "Ninkyō dantai"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Conrad Reed sparked one of these events in Cabarrus County in 1799. The folk song “Mursheen Durkin” recounts the story of a participant in one of these events. Many participants in one of these events traveled to it via the Siskiyou (20 pts)",
        "Trail. One of these events was publicized in Samuel Brannon’s California Star newspaper and was kickstarted by a (10 pts)",
        "discovery made by James W. Marshall. For ten points, identify these types of events, one of which famously occurred following an 1849 discovery at Sutter’s Mill."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gold Rushes",
        "Carolina Gold Rush",
        "California Gold Rush",
        "prompt on answers relating to the discovery of \"gold\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2021, this island used commemorative coins to celebrate its 140th anniversary of giving some women the right to vote in 1881. This island was ceded by Magnus VI [[the Sixth]] of Norway to Alexander III of (20 pts)",
        "Scotland under the Treaty of Perth in 1266. This island’s legislature, the Tynwald [[TIN-wahld]], claims to be the “oldest continuous parliament” in the world, celebrating its millennium in (10 pts)",
        "1979. Known in recent history for its tax-haven status and money-laundering controversies, for ten points, what is this island crown dependency located between Great Britain and Ireland?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Isle of Man or Mannin",
        "or Ellan Vannin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This historian asked \"Why were patricians not permitted to live on the Capitoline?\" as the ninety-first in a series of Questions in one of his works. A set of “Sayings of Spartans” was collected by this one-time priest at the Temple of (20 pts)",
        "Delphi in a work which also contains an often-cited account of Egyptian burial rites, the Moralia [[moh-RAH-lyah]]. This author is best known for a work containing 48 biographies which are grouped into (10 pts)",
        "pairs featuring one Greek and one Roman. For ten points, name this Roman historian who wrote Parallel Lives."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Plutarch or Ploutarchos",
        "Plutarch's Lives 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    }
  ]
}